Finding Aid for Law Library (University of Michigan) Records 1859-2006
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Law Library (University of Michigan) Records
1859-2006
1930-1995
University of Michigan. Law Library.
The Law Library was established as part of the University of Michigan Law School in 1859 and is currently maintained and administered as a part of the instructional and research operation of the Law School. The collection contains documentation related to administrative matters within the Law Library, including financial documentation, correspondence, director files, and documentation on the building expansion of the library. The collection also contains some of the material removed from the collections at the library, as well as documentation related to the Law School, which was also previously housed in the library collections.
87236 Bimu C430 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
22 linear feet
25 oversize items
1 oversize folders
The record group (donor no. 1667 ) was transferred to the Bentley Library in November 1982. Subsequent small accessions were received in 1984, 1990 and 1999.
The records are open for research.
The Law School of the University of Michigan was founded in October 1859. Earlier in April of the same year, the Regents appropriated $2,000 for the establishment of a law library. In addition, in October 1859, Judge Thomas M. Cooley of Detroit donated 350 volumes to the library. These volumes formed the basis of the library's collection. During the 19th century the Law Library received three major gifts; one from Judge Richard Fletcher of Boston in 1866 of 800 volumes, and two others from Detroit businessman Christian H. Buhl. In 1886 Buhl donated his personal library of over 5,000 volumes to the Law Library. This increased the size of the collection to nearly 10,000 volumes. In 1894 Buhl gave the library $10,000. With this bequest the library was able to increase substantially the scope of its collection. In 1929, William Cook, a beneficiary of the Law School, donated his entire personal collection to the library, and had the room in which his collection had been housed reconstructed in the library to house the material there.
Originally the collection consisted mainly of reports from Michigan, Pennsylvania, New York, and some New England states. The early focus of the library's collection was judicial decisions rather than acts of legislatures. However, in 1886, the library began a campaign to obtain statutes from all states in the Union. The money received from the Buhl bequest also helped the library to purchase and develop a section on foreign law. Up to that time the library held volumes relating only to American and English law. Throughout the early 20th century, acquisition of materials concerning foreign law and international law gave the library one of the best collections in the United States.
The first three law librarians, Isaac Marston, Levi L. Barbour, and William R. Day, were all students in the Law School. Joseph H. Vance served as the first full-time librarian from 1883 to 1899. In 1899, Judge Victor Lane became the law librarian and presided over a collection of roughly 18,000 volumes. He did not oversee the administrative duties of the library, but rather concentrated on teaching, research, and collection development. The day-to-day activities of the library were the responsibilities of his assistant librarians: Gertrude Woodard (1901-1915), Elizabeth Steere (1915-1918), Blanche Harroun (1918-1924), and Rebecca Wilson (1924-1927). These women, led by Woodard, brought the collection under organizational control through the use of modern library principles and practices. Professor Hobart R. Coffey succeeded Judge Lane as law librarian, a position he held from 1926 to 1966. By 1937 the library contained 133,000 volumes. Professor Coffey's assistant librarian, Esther Betz, worked at the library from 1927 to 1963. Professor Beverly Pooley became the law librarian in 1965, a position he held until 1985. From 1985 until 1995 Pooley served as associate dean of the Law Library. Margaret Leary became director of the library in 1985. In 2011 Barbara H. Garavaglia moved from assistant director to full director of the Law Library.
The Law Library was first located in the south wing of University Hall and then moved to the Law Building in 1863. The library moved to its present location, the William W. Cook Legal Research Building, in 1931. After much debate, the library underwent major renovation in 1980 to expand into the area underneath the Legal Research Building. The award-winning underground addition to the Law Library was designed by architect Gunnar Birkerts. In 1986 the library was officially designated as the Allen F. and Alene Smith Law Library.
The Law Library's purpose is to build collections and provide services to support the teaching and research needs of Law School faculty and students. The Law Library's collections, services, and policies are primarily designed to benefit the Law School's faculty and students, and others officially connected with the Law School. The Law Library's secondary users are other University of Michigan faculty and students who have legitimate need to use the collection, and attorneys. As of 2013, the Law Library held 1,044,561 total volumes in both paper and microform format. Current information on the Law Library is available at the following URL: http://www.law.umich.edu/library/
For more information on the Law School, researchers are advised to examine the Law School record group also housed at the Bentley Historical Library.
The material included in the Law Library records are primarily the files of the library directors and of Professor Hobart R. Coffey and Esther Betz. The material included in the Law Library records are divided into five series: Administration, Collections, Law School, Audio Visual Material, and William Cook Papers.
Subjects:
Cooperative societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Law.; Legal Microfilms Association.; Libraries--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Michigan Wolverine Student Cooperative (University of Michigan); University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.; Law Library Addition (University of Michigan)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
University of Michigan--Law School.Law School.; Thomas M. Cooley lectures.; William Warner Bishop lectureship series.; William W. Cook Foundation lectures.
Contributors:
Betz, Esther.; Coffey, Hobart R., 1896-1969.
Genre/Form:
Sound recordings.
- Administration
  The Administration series contains documents and records relating directly to the operation of the Law Library. Contained within are ten subseries.
  - Director's Files, 1919-1963
    The Director's Files concern the administration of the library. There are also topical files created by Professor Coffey relating mainly to his own personal activities. Specific areas of strength within the Director's Files include the Michigan Wolverine Student Cooperative, the Legal Microfilms Association, Professor Coffey's South American Research Tour, and minutes of the Law Library Committee.
    - Addresses, 1929-1948; 4 folders (Box 1)
    - American Association of Law Libraries, 1949-1953; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - American Bar Association, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
    - American Library Association, 1949-1954 (Box 1)
    - Annual Reports, 1941/42-1951/52 (Box 1)
    - Books: Purchase and Sale, 1932-1942 (Box 1)
    - Building Committee, 1944 (Box 1)
    - Business Office, 1931-1942 (Box 1)
    - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1932-1933 (Box 1)
    - Case Club Prize Books, 1935-1939 (Box 1)
    - Civil Works Administration, 1934 (Box 1)
    - Class Reunion, 1924 (Box 1)
    - Committee on cooperation with Latin American Libraries, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
    - Committee on Research, 1939-1950 (Box 1)
    - Committee Reports: Miscellaneous, 1936-1943 (Box 1)
    - Cook Fund Committee, 1935-1936 (Box 1)
    - Crime and Criminology, 1934-1938 (Box 1)
    - Curriculum Committee, 1936-1947 (Box 1)
    - Dean, Law School, 1945-1955; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Delta Theta Phi, 1927-1945 (Box 1)
    - Domestic Relations Committee, 1948-1955 (Box 1)
    - Editorial Committee, 1943-1949 (Box 1)
    - First Annual Autograph Collectors Meeting, 1948 (Box 1)
    - General Law School Files, 1943-1949; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - General Library, 1925-1945 (Box 1)
    - General Library Council, 1946-1949 (Box 1)
    - Law Library Committee Minutes, 1922-1952 (Box 2)
    - Lawyers' Club Book Fund, 1946-1951 (Box 2)
    - League of Nations-Non-Partisan Association, 1926-1940 (Box 2)
    - Legal Microfilms Association, 1937-1953; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Legal Research Building, 1927-1940; 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Librarian's Report, 1932-1940 (Box 2)
    - Libraries of Major Universities, 1929-1943 (Box 2)
    - Library and Schools, 1931-1945 (Box 2)
    - Library of Congress, 1929-1946 (Box 2)
    - Library Positions, 1940-1942 (Box 2)
    - Library Routine, 1957 (Box 2)
    - Library Rules, 1928-1931 (Box 2)
    - Memoranda, 1929-1952; 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Law Review, 1932-1944 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Library Association, 1933-1949; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Michigan State Bar, 1937-1949 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State Board for Libraries, 1935-1939 (Box 3)
    - Michigan State Library, 1946-1947 (Box 3)
    - Michigan Wolverine Student Cooperative, 1935-1952; 9 folders (Box 3)
    - Microfilms, 1931-1943 (Box 4)
    - Munich Seminar, 1926 (Box 4)
    - National Youth Administration, 1934-1942 (Box 4)
    - Personal File, 1941-1943 (Box 4)
    - Quarto Notes, 1943-1944 (Box 4)
    - Rabel, Ernst, 1943-1950; 4 folders (Box 4)
    - Reference, 1949-1963; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Senate, University of Michigan, 1949-1950 (Box 4)
    - South American Tour, 1949-1950; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Statistics, 1919-1941; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Student Assistants, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Teachers' Tenure, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
    - United States Supreme Court Imprints (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan, 1941-1949 (Box 5)
    - Viollet Collection, 1944 (Box 5)
    - Wilgus List, 1933 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, 1924-1965
    The Correspondence Files contain correspondence of Professor Coffey, various library directors from 1962 to 1990, and Esther Betz. Professor Coffey's correspondence is broken down chronologically then alphabetically. These have been retained in the order maintained by Professor Coffey. Correspondence of miscellaneous directors follows the original alphabetical arrangement. Esther Betz's correspondences are organized chronologically. The correspondence files that were added in box 14 are organized alphabetically, per the original order.
    - Hobart R. Coffey
      - 1924-1944
        - B-S, 14 folders (Box 5)
        - T-Z, 4 folders (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - 1945-1949
        - A-Z, 9 folders (Box 6)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
      - 1950-1965
        - A-L, 7 folders (Box 6)
        - M-Y, 7 folders (Box 7)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Directors
      - 1962-1990
        - A-Z, 21 folders (Box 7)
    - Esther Betz
      - 1926-1929 (Box 7)
      - 1930-1939 (Box 7)
      - 1940-1949 (Box 7)
      - 1950-1959 (Box 7)
      - 1960-1962 (Box 7)
  - History
    The History subseries includes reports and a listing of Regents Proceedings pertinent to the development of the Law Library from 1858 through 1934, proceedings of the Library Committee, and miscellaneous statistics and reports.
    - History of Law Library, 1858-1937 (Box 8)
    - Proceedings of Library Committee, 1898-1906 (Box 8)
    - Miscellanea (includes circulation statistics, reports, memos), 1907-1912 (Box 8)
    - List of Current Foreign Legal Periodicals Received, 1958-1975; 4 volumes (Box 8)
  - Library Administration Materials
    The Library Administration Materials contains information related to changes in the library field, such as the introduction to the Anglo-American Cataloging Rules II and the RLG Serials Project, and how the Law Library reacted. This subseries also contains background information and files from the Library Advisory Committee, overarching objectives, evaluation, and planning by the Law Library, and materials related to a bibliography of Festschriften (homage publications), compiled by Lily Roberts. Also found in this subseries are files on gifts received by the Law Library from 1958-1980, and by two individuals in particular: John Star Hunt and Virginia Earl.
    - Anglo-American Cataloging Rules II (AACR2) Memos (Box 8)
    - Festschriften (Box 8)
    - Library Advisory Committee Background Materials, 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Library Advisory Committee, 1983-1986 (Box 8)
    - Law Library Objectives, Evaluation, Planning (Box 8)
    - Law Library Gifts
      - 1958-1959 (Box 8)
      - 1965-1974 (Box 8)
      - 1975-1979 (Box 8)
      - 1980 (Box 8)
      - John Star Hunt (Box 8)
      - Virginia Earl (Box 8)
    - RLG/Ballots, 1978-1979 (Box 8)
    - RLG/RLIN Serials Conversion Project (Box 8)
  - Library Building Addition (1980), 1969-1990
    The Library Building Addition subseries includes documents related to the major renovation that occurred in 1980. Of particular importance is the debate whether or not to construct the new library underground. In addition to the manuscript materials is one folder of architectural drawings. The drawings relate to proposals from various architects for the library building addition. The drawings include exterior elevations, plot plans, and renderings of interiors. Additional material on the design of the award-winning underground addition to the library may be found in the records of Gunnar Birkerts and Associates. Birkerts designed the addition and the records of his architectural firm are held at the Bentley Library.
    The bulk of the Library Building Addition files were added in 2006. These files include Building Committee Files which contain all materials related to the library addition, including correspondence between library administration and the architect, Gunnar Birkerts and Associates, as well as questionnaires, reports, and sketches of proposed additions to the law library. This collection also houses newspaper clippings and published articles related to the University of Michigan's project, compared to other academic library additions being built during this same period. The Student Building Committee is also represented in this collection.
    - Architectural drawings and renderings of proposals for an addition to the law library building, ca. 1960s (Map-case 224)
    - Building Committee
      - 1969-1972 (Box 8)
      - 1973 (Box 8)
      - (folder 1), 1974 (Box 8)
      - (folder 2), 1974 (Box 9)
      - 1975 (Box 9)
      - 1976, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - 1977, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - 1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - 1979 (Box 9)
      - 1980-1990 (Box 9)
    - Newspaper Articles Relevant to Library Building Addition (Box 9)
    - Publications Related to Academic Library Additions/Construction in the United States (Box 9)
    - Published Material Relevant to Library Buildings, 1976-1977 (Box 9)
    - Student Building Committee, 1976 (Box 9)
  - Acquisitions, 1969-2006
    The Acquisitions subseries contains documents related to the various material that the library would attempt to procure for its collections. This includes primarily correspondence with other institutes because the library was interested in purchasing materials, confirming or cancelling a subscription, or because the library was attempting to complete collections of documents or magazines that were only partially held at the library.
    - African Imprints, 1987 (Box 13)
    - American Collection Development, 1985-1987 (Box 13)
    - American Law Institute, 1987 (Box 13)
    - American Selections, 1986-2000 (Box 13)
    - Ancillary Publications, 1987-1989 (Box 13)
    - Bangladesh Acquisitions Program, 1982-1984 (Box 13)
    - British Material, 1973-1983; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - British Material, 1975-1988 (Box 13)
    - British Publications, 1970-1983 (Box 13)
    - British Record Society, 1984-1985 (Box 13)
    - Casebook Supplement, 1987; 1991 (Box 13)
    - Carlton Fox Material, 1980-1990 (Box 13)
    - Cook, Cooley, and Bishop Lectures, 1980; 1989 (Box 13)
    - Court Rules, 1980-1986 (Box 13)
    - Egyptian Material PL. 480, 1979-1981 (Box 13)
    - European Union Material, 1983-1993 (Box 13)
    - Exchange Problem, 1979-1991 (Box 13)
    - Foreign Law, 1984-1988 (Box 13)
    - Foreign Material General, 1972-1984 (Box 13)
    - Fourth Russell Tribunal, 1987 (Box 13)
    - French Material, 1978-1981 (Box 13)
    - German Material, 1974-1978 (Box 13)
    - Government Documents, 1974-1984; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Harrossowitz Order, 1972 (Box 13)
    - Index to Foreign Legal Periodicals, 1986; 1991 (Box 13)
    - India Material PL. 480, 1969-1978 (Box 13)
    - International Encyclopedia of Comparative Law, 1983 (Box 13)
    - International Organizations and Collections, 1976-1983 (Box 13)
    - Islamic and South Asia Material PL. 480, 1997; 2003 (Box 13)
    - Islamic Law Collection, 1979-1982 (Box 13)
    - Japanese Material, 1978-1981 (Box 13)
    - Mexican Material, 1978-1983 (Box 13)
    - Middle East Acquisitions Program, 1981-1984 (Box 13)
    - Moody's Purchasing Agreement, 1979-1983 (Box 13)
    - National Reporter System, 1979 (Box 13)
    - Public Utility Commission, 1983-1984; 2001-2002 (Box 13)
    - Regional Digests, 1974-1982 (Box 14)
    - Restatements, 1980-1982 (Box 14)
    - Satellite Collections, 1979-1980 (Box 14)
    - Science Magazine, 1982 (Box 14)
    - Supreme Court Records and Briefs, 1974-1993 (Box 14)
    - Texas Material, 1980 (Box 14)
    - Treatises, 1976; 2005-2006 (Box 14)
  - Construction, 1967-1995; 2000
    The Construction subseries contains material that is separate from the main library addition that was constructed in 1980. This subseries includes records related to the construction of the Rare Book Room and the Computer-Assisted Research Room, as well as a staff Tea Room.
    - Computer Assisted Legal Research Room, 1993-1994 (Box 14)
    - Law School Expansion Final Report, Venturi, Scott Brown and Associates, May 2000 (Box 22)
    - Tea Lounge, 1967-1991 (Box 14)
    - Rare Book Room, 1990-1995 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z (Box 14)
    - D-F (Box 14)
    - G-H (Box 14)
    - I-K (Box 14)
    - L-M (Box 14)
    - N-P (Box 14)
    - R-S (Box 14)
    - T-Z (Box 14)
  - Depository, 1978-2003
    The Depository subseries is made up of general information about the library depository and the records of the inspections of the depository.
    - General, 1978-2003 (Box 14)
    - Inspection, 1988; 1994; 2002; 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Program Review, 1986-1994 (Box 14)
    - Self-study Program, 2002 (Box 14)
  - Financial, 1859-1979
    The Financial subseries contains primarily budget files, as well as records on the five-year projection and salary funds.
    - Budget, 1859-1955; 1962-1979; 17 folders (Box 15)
    - Documents, 1859-1962; 1973-1976 (Box 15)
    - Five-year Projection, 1972-1974 (Box 15)
    - Projections, 1969-1971 (Box 15)
    - Salary Funds, 1929-1969 (Box 16)
  - Policies and Procedures, 1945; 1975-2004
    The Policies and Procedures contain manuals and instructions related to the acquiring and maintenance of the material in the Law Library. This includes procedural manuals and collection strategy manuals.
    - Book Selection Process, 1980-1987 (Box 16)
    - Cataloging Manual, 1975-1995 (Box 16)
    - Claim Codes and Issues, 1989-2002 (Box 16)
    - Clerical Manual, 1987 (Box 16)
    - Collection Development, 1984-1990; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Dictionaries Collection, 1986-1995 (Box 16)
    - Grievance Procedures, 1980-1984 (Box 16)
    - Insurance, 1989 (Box 16)
    - International Collection, 1990-1992 (Box 16)
    - Microform Procedures, 1975-1985; 1990-2004; 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Photocopying Policy, 1986-1987 (Box 16)
    - Procedure Manual (Box 16)
    - Selection Policy, 1945 (Box 16)
    - Standards for Written Documents, 1999 (Box 16)
    - Statistics Policy, 1999 (Box 16)
    - Subject Matter, 1979-1986; 2005 (Box 16)
    - UN and EC Material, 1989-1992 (Box 16)
    - Yellow Block Policy, 1982-1992 (Box 16)
  - Topical, 19974-1998
    The Topical subseries contains documents from the advisory committee, annual reports, blueprints, information on the microform and looseleaf services at the library, and other various documents.
    - AACR2 (Box 16)
    - Advisory Committee, 1991-1997 (Box 16)
    - Annual Reports, 1979-1997 (Box 16)
    - Checklist Project, 1974-1983 (Box 17)
    - Committee on Disability, 1993-1995 (Box 17)
    - Constitutional Conventions, 1976-1984 (Box 17)
    - Court Slip Opinions, 1986-1989 (Box 17)
    - Government Printing Office Conversion to Fiche, 1981 (Box 17)
    - Lateral Files, 1987 (Box 17)
    - Law Library Microform Orders, 1978-1988 (Box 17)
    - Looseleaf Services, 1974-1986; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Move of Reference Services and Collection, 1988 (Box 17)
    - Newspaper Clippings (Box 17)
    - Rare Books, 1986-1993 (Box 17)
    - State Administrative Codes, 1975-1994 (Box 17)
    - State Administrative Reports, 1981-1984 (Box 17)
    - Transnational Research, 1984 (Box 17)
    - University Microforms International, 1940-1982 (Box 17)
    - UN Withdrawals, 1997-1998 (Box 17)
    - Workflow Flow Charts, 1982 (Box 17)
- Collections
  The Collections series is made up of material that was previously held at the Law Library in their collections but was then removed and donated to the Bentley Historical Library. This includes various documents, such as Law School publications, and notes on various lectures that were given at the university by James Campbell and James B. Angell. Significant material on the Michigan Law Review is contained here, including founding documents, article of associations, minutes, and a history file containing correspondence from several notable figures. Correspondents include Supreme Court justices Louis Brandeis, James Byrnes, and Harlan Stone as well as Attorney General Francis Biddle, Senator Arthur Vandenberg, and alumnus John D. Voelker.
  Within this is a subseries of Collected Late 18th and 19th Century Documents. In 1984, the law library added these documents to their holdings at the Bentley, which it had received from various sources, mainly former faculty and alumni. Included are various legal instruments, certificates of indenture, commissions, and appointments. There is also a register of cases prepared by law student Dwight May, and a volume of a law periodical kept by Albert J. Chapman. Many of the documents are oversize.
  - Late 18th and 19th Century Documents
    - Recommendation for Aaron Wait made by Benjamin Osgood (see also outsize documents), 1847 (Box 9)
    - Register of Cases (course notebook of Dwight May), 1861-1873 (Box 9)
    - Bench and Bar (Box 9)
      (from library of Albert J. Chapman, including notes and tipped-in letters from James V. Campbell and Charles Sumner)
    - Goodrich family indentures and other legal instruments (Box 9)
      (see also outsize documents)
    - Miscellanea (including pencil sketch of Otto Kirchner) (Folder 1)
    - Unbound manuscripts
      (Bimu/C430)
      - Appointment of George Morell to Michigan Supreme Court, 1843 (Folder 1)
      - Appointments of Aaron Wait, 1843; 2 items (Folder 1)
      - Goodrich family indentures and other legal documents, 13 items (Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 5 items (Folder 1)
  - Collections, 1902-1954
    - Advocacy Institute, 1953; 1955-1959; 6 folders (Box 17)
    - Charles Kent Memorial (Box 17)
    - Committee of Visitors, 1964; 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Committee of Visitors Annual Meeting, 1963